<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epithalamium upon the marriage of Capt. William Bedloe</title>
            <author>Duke, Richard, 1658-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2504B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R228922</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897237</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897237</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135142</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81816)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135142)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2483:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epithalamium upon the marriage of Capt. William Bedloe</title>
                  <author>Duke, Richard, 1658-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Richard Duke--Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Verse - "Goddess of rhime, that didst inspire".</note>
                  <note>Printed in two columns.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bedloe, William, 1650-1680 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:135142:1"/>
            <head>AN EPITHALAMIUM UPON THE MARRIAGE OF Capt. William Bedloe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ille ego qui quondam gracili modulatus Avena,</l>
                     <l>Arma virumque Cano.—</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I, he, who Sung of Humble</hi> Oates <hi>before,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Now ſing a</hi> Captain <hi>and a Man of WAR.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <l>GOddeſs of Rhime, that didſt inſpire</l>
               <l>The <hi>Captain</hi> with Poetick fire,</l>
               <l>Adding freſh Lawrells to that brow</l>
               <l>Where thoſe of Victory did grow,</l>
               <l>And ſtatelyer ornaments may flouriſh now.</l>
               <l>If thou art well recover'd ſince</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Excommunicated Prince:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For that Important Tragedy,</l>
               <l>Would have kill'd any Muſe but Thee;</l>
               <l>Hither with ſpeed, oh! hither move,</l>
               <l>Pull buskins off, and ſince to love</l>
               <l>The ground is holy that you tread in,</l>
               <l>Dance bare-foot at the <hi>Captains</hi> Wedding.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>See where he comes, and by his ſide</l>
               <l>His Charming fair Angelick Bride:</l>
               <l>Such, or leſs lovely was the Dame</l>
               <l>So much Renown'd, <hi>Fulvia</hi> by name,</l>
               <l>With whom of old <hi>Tully</hi> did joyn,</l>
               <l>Then when his Art did undermine,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Horrid Popiſh Plot</hi> of <hi>Cateline.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oh faireſt Nymph of all great <hi>Brittain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Though the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my Eyes I never ſet on)</l>
               <l>Bluſh not on thy great Lord to ſmile,</l>
               <l>The ſecond Saviour of our Iſle;</l>
               <l>What nobler Captain could have led,</l>
               <l>Thee to thy long'd-for marriage bed:</l>
               <l>For know that thy all-daring <hi>Will</hi> is</l>
               <l>As ſtout a <hi>Hero</hi> as <hi>Achilles;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And as great things for thee has done,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Palmerin</hi> or th' <hi>Knight of th' Sun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And is himſelf a whole Romance alone.</l>
               <l>Let conſcious <hi>Flanders</hi> ſpeak, and be,</l>
               <l>The Witneſs of his Chivalry.</l>
               <l>Yet that's not all, his very word</l>
               <l>Has ſlain as many as his ſword:</l>
               <l>Though common Bulleys with their Oaths</l>
               <l>Hurt little till they come to blows,</l>
               <l>Yet all his <hi>Mouth-Granadoes</hi> kill</l>
               <l>And ſave the pains of drawing ſteel.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:135142:2"/>
               <l>This <hi>Hero</hi> thy reſiſtleſs charms</l>
               <l>Have won to fly into thy arms,</l>
               <l>For think not any mean deſign</l>
               <l>Or the inglorious itch of coyne,</l>
               <l>Could ever have his breaſt contrould,</l>
               <l>Or make him be a ſlave to Gold;</l>
               <l>His Love's as freely given to Thee</l>
               <l>As to the King his Loyalty.</l>
               <l>Then oh receive thy mighty prize</l>
               <l>With open arms and wiſhing eyes,</l>
               <l>Kiſſe that dear face where may be ſeen</l>
               <l>His worth and parts that ſculk within,</l>
               <l>That face that juſtly ſtil'd may be</l>
               <l>As true a Diſcoverer as He.</l>
               <l>Think not he ever falſe will prove,</l>
               <l>His well known truth ſecures his love;</l>
               <l>Do you awhile divert his cares</l>
               <l>From his important grand affairs:</l>
               <l>Let him have reſpite now awhile</l>
               <l>From kindling the mad rabbles zeal.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Zeal that is hot as fire, yet dark and blind</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shews plainly where its birth-place we may finde,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In hell, where tho' dire flames for ever glow</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet 'tis the place of utter darkneſs too.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But to his bed be ſure be true</l>
               <l>As he to all the World and you,</l>
               <l>He all your plots will elſe betray</l>
               <l>That your She-<hi>Machiavills</hi> can lay.</l>
               <l>He all deſigns you know has found,</l>
               <l>Tho hatch'd in Hell, or under ground;</l>
               <l>Did oft to us ſuch ſecrets ſhew</l>
               <l>As ſcarce the Plotters themſelves knew,</l>
               <l>Yet if by chance you hap to ſin</l>
               <l>And love while Honour's napping ſhou'd creep in.</l>
               <l>Yet be diſcreet and do not boaſt</l>
               <l>Oth' treaſon by the common poſt.</l>
               <l>So ſhalt thou ſtill make him love on</l>
               <l>All virtues in Diſcretion.</l>
               <l>So thou with him ſhalt ſhine, and be</l>
               <l>As great a Patriot as He;</l>
               <l>And when, (as now in <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> all</l>
               <l>For a new pack of Cards do call,)</l>
               <l>Another Popiſh Pack comes out</l>
               <l>To pleaſe the Cits, and charm the rout;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou mighty Queen ſhal't a whole Suit Command,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Crown upon thy Head, and Sceptre in thy Hand.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
